[Music]
one
two three
[Music]
easy
hi good afternoon everyone my name is
ping welcome to the media launch of our
new research
saving for 100 funding longevity in a
time of uncertainty
saving for 100 is part of prudential's
ready for 100
thought leadership program which aims to
find out the readiness
and aspirations of singaporeans in
living longer lives
when we started this program with the
economist intelligence unit in 2018
we uncovered many interesting insights
for instance we found that while
singaporeans are avid savers
many of them will struggle to save
enough to retire at 65
and leave without an income until 100.
so this finding prompted us to dive
deeper
and we decided to evolve the discussion
with this latest report focused on
finances
to give us expert insights into this
very important topic
i have a panel of subject matter experts
in the studio with me today
let me take some time to introduce them
to my right here
mr aberlin executive director head of
wealth management advisory
bursner financial services at uob with
20 years of experience in the advisory
business
aber leads a team of portfolio
counsellors and strategists
he oversees the investment portfolio and
strategic direction of uob's personal
financial services segment
we also have mr dennis tan ceo of
prudential singapore
a veteran banker dennis has 26 years of
experience in consumer banking
spanning product development segment
management
marketing sales and distribution and
last but not least
we have miss doncha don runs a blog on
personal finances
her blog has received more than 11
million visitors
and is ranked as one of the world's top
60 budget
well without further ado let me now pass
the time over to dennis tan prudential
singapore ceo
to say a few words about this research
dennis
thanks very much ping good afternoon
everyone and thank you for joining us
this afternoon for the launch
of prudential's saving for 100 research
report
now some of you may be wondering why did
prudential commission this study
together with the economist intelligence
unit
and the study on longevity well the
short answer is that we want to really
understand this topic
a lot better and we want to really help
singaporeans
live well for longer as we all know
singaporeans are beginning to live
longer and longer today more than one in
two singaporeans
at age 65 will be expected to live
beyond 85 and in fact 1 in 3
will be living beyond 90 years old
so in order to ensure that we are not
just living
longer we all want to live longer and
live
well so for that we really need to work
together
to really look towards financial
planning and investing and savings
for the long haul so that we have enough
savings
into our golden years well very
interestingly from the research
we found that 56 percent of singaporeans
are confident that they will have this
retirement essay and they are well
equipped
to save for this future but what that
means is that
another sizeable portion are actually
feeling
quite ill prepared for that and that is
an opportunity for us to work on
however that's it i'm also heartened to
to know that the
younger singaporeans and the millennials
are feeling actually very positive and
confident
about having enough savings for the
lifetime
in fact from the research it shows that
three in five millennials
who are savers have experienced and have
expressed
this confidence well longevity
comes with it challenges as well as
opportunities
and i think it's important for us to all
embrace the opportunities
that living a long life will bring to
all of us and for that to happen it's
important that we start financial
planning
earlier younger so that there's a long
runway ahead
for us to work towards their financial
goals and i think the other thing is
importantly having that long runway is
to help us
prepare and cushion for uncertainties in
life
disruptions and situations such as the
covet-19 pandemic that we see right now
so as the old saying goes if we fail to
if we fail to prepare we prepare to fail
i say again if we fail to prepare
we prepare to fail so it's important
that we continue to work
towards having those financial plans in
place
to prevent for the eventuality well
prudential has developed
a whole suite of products and solutions
to help our customers and to help the
public
to work towards this longevity and such
examples of having products that cater
to
up to 100 years old these are all highly
customizable solutions
that will help us work towards the
demands of extended
lifespan so we hope that by joining us
this afternoon
this will stimulate our thinking and
together with the
expert panel that we have and the
sharing let's think about
living to 100 saving to 100
and preparing ourselves to 100 why so
we want to do that because we want to
all live well
for longer thank you for joining us
well thank you very much dennis indeed
like it or not we are all going to live
longer so as dennis said
good financial planning is key to ensure
we have adequate savings
to embrace the opportunities that a
longer life presents
so before we go into the panel
discussion and the q a
let me take some time now to share the
key findings from the saving for 100
research
as i mentioned earlier saving for 100 is
the research conducted by the economist
intelligence unit and commissioned by
prudential singapore
for this report we spoke to 1200
singapore residents to get their views
they were split equally almost equally
between agendas 51 percent men
49 women and equally across the 4-h
brackets from age 25 to 65
our respondents fall into four income
categories
sixty percent earn between sixty to a
hundred thousand per annum
well besides the um quantitative survey
we also interviewed subject matter
experts for their views on this topic
this expert comes from the cpa board the
ministry of manpower the center for
seniors
the national university of singapore and
the financial services industry
in fact two of the pan two of our
panelists today aberlin from uob
and doncha they were interviewed for
this research
well let's now take a look at what
singaporeans are saying about
saving for 100.
so one of the first questions that we
asked respondents was
are you confident about saving enough to
support leaving until you die
more than half you can see here 56
percent said they felt confident
well now this is a pretty encouraging
you know piece of number
those age 55 to 65 feel the most
confident almost seven in ten from this
age group say they will be financially
ready for longevity
in general men felt more confident than
women
and between the income brackets as you
can see those earning more felt more
confident finally those expecting to
leave to 80 or older
felt more confident than those expecting
to leave between 60 and 79.
i guess if you are expecting to live
long you are going to prepare well for
it
now let's come back to the first few
bars what really stood out for us when
we analyzed the results
was that three out of five millennials
they believe that they will be able to
build a nest egg robust enough to
finance their lifestyles and old
age these are the younger singaporeans
aged between 25
to 34. in comparison their older
counterparts those aged between 35 to 44
feel the least optimistic so there you
have it the confidence level
of singaporeans in their ability to save
for longevity
now we also ask respondents how they are
saving
or planning to save for longevity there
is recognition among singaporeans of the
need to diversify their income streams
if they want to have
enough for retirement so as you can see
here
they are using a wide range of financial
matters and instruments to protect
as well as to grow their wealth cpf
is the most popular financial instrument
of respondents say they are relying on
cpf to finance their old age
this is followed by bank savings such as
fixed deposits
and life insurance now the more
aggressive savers are looking to
investments
in stocks and real estate
so our respondents also say they need to
invest more of their savings to grow
their wealth
millennials seem to be more tolerant of
risk in their financial strategies than
older generations
72 percent of millennials compared with
66 percent of the overall sample say
they will need to invest
more of their savings to ensure they can
fund a longer life
and they are considering higher risk
assets such as
equities and exchange-traded securities
as part of their portfolio
this financial savviness could be one of
the reasons why millennials are
confident
of having enough savings for oh
well while millennials are confident of
their financial future
and are taking steps towards
safeguarding it the truth is
they will be challenged by financial
responsibilities towards family
as you can see from the chart here
millennials 89
of millennial respondents they expect to
financially support their aging parents
they and 71 expect to financially
support their children
and grandchildren but only slightly more
than 30 percent expect their children to
provide for them
when they retire well this is not really
surprising i mean given the ongoing
decline in family size
half of today's millennials do not think
it is practical to have more than one
child
what this means is that there will be
fewer people to share financial
responsibilities
well besides family responsibilities
health care expenditure
that's another challenge or concern
identified by the respondents
when we ask them what they are saving
for healthcare
came up top on the list and this can be
due to concerns around rising medical
inflation
and the potential of having multiple
chronic diseases as one becomes
older as you can see here 8 in 10
respondents
listed healthcare as their top saving
priority
and this is followed by trevor
supporting elderly parents
and pursuing leisure activities
well and finally the research also shows
us that evolving lifestyles could impact
retirement financing
with rising lifespans people are moving
away
from the traditional three-stage life of
study work
and retirement into a multi-stage life
this means people are planning for more
than one occupation
they are going back to school during
their mid-life to pursue a second degree
and they are taking career breaks as
well you know during
basically during their working life in
fact
47 percent of respondents say they plan
to take career breaks
during their working life more
millennial respondents
52 percent have this expectation
so this chart here shows what
singaporeans
want to take career breaks for as you
can see
mainly to trevor to tend to family
and interestingly also to study and to
pick up a new skill
with an eye to changing occupations
so to summarize our key findings
singaporeans they are mostly confident
two in three millennia say they have
already saved or will be able to save
enough to support leaving until they die
to prepare for the future singaporeans
are always practical they are using
diverse financial methods and
instruments to grow their wealth
they recognize the need to take risk and
they plan to invest more of their
savings
to fund their older age millennials are
the most
open to higher risk assets
but singaporeans especially the
millennials they will feel challenged by
financial pressures of taking care of
their parents
and children and in addition to the duty
of care to their family
singaporeans have their own personal
aspirations to finance
millennials more so than older groups
plan to take
several career breaks in a lifetime
with so many responsibilities and a
desire to experience all that life has
to offer
how can singaporeans safe enough to meet
their goals
millennials they seem to want it all
they want to take care of the family
they want to have career breaks
and they want to pursue their passions
how can they prepare for all of these
goals and desires
well let's hear what our panelists have
to say
you know about this findings and this
insights i'm going to start the ball
rolling with a couple of questions
and then i'll open up the floor for q a
well i hope all of you found this you
know for the research insights
interesting
i'm going to ask you a few questions to
hear thoughts about the insights and and
why do you think
you know the insights are such so the
first question i'm going to
ask dennis you know the first question
as we can
see um we all know that singaporeans are
very avid savers
you know yet many will struggle to save
enough to leave to 100.
so the research shows that 56 percent
say they are confident
but another 44 say that they are not
confident
of saving enough for retirement um
how do you think we can all better save
for extended longevity
well if you ask me in terms of saving
for 100
there's no shortcuts right at the same
time it's also not
that difficult in the sense that as long
as we
start early and have a plan i think
importantly is to have that plan
and have the discipline towards that
planning process
and once we have that we will be able to
work towards that long-run way
to prepare for the un unthinkable in
time to come
right so uncertainties that may come
along the way and all that as long as we
have
the passage of time i think planning is
very very important
well just now i think earlier you showed
the chart and i was quite intrigued with
uh
one of the charts that showed that
actually the the different instruments
that the respondents said that they are
using to save towards towards 100
right or safe towards longevity i
thought that was important
because people are looking at using
different instruments right cpf we saw
that
bank deposits but equally also i saw in
there
very interestingly right besides just
cash it was also
life insurance and health insurance and
that rank
quite similarly to stocks and bonds as
well right so it shows that people are
actually quite open to all forms of
instruments as in this important that
they continue
to use those instruments to work towards
their financial plans
to meet their goals and finally i think
one one point to note is
from my perspective what is important is
also the risk appetite
right so we all are different we have
different risk appetites
so it's important for individuals to get
in touch and better understand what your
attitudes are towards your own personal
receptor for yourself and for your
family
and as you factor that into your
financial planning
well thanks so much dennis so as dennis
said no shortcuts
start planning early if you want to
leave well for longer
abel can i get a view from you how do
you think singaporeans can prepare
better for longevity um to echo then
it's just point
i think it's also equally important to
consider the length of time that you
have
in terms of your financial plan i think
dennis covered it earlier
start as early as possible okay start as
regularly as possible
and at the same time start as
comfortably as possible because
affordability is incredibly important as
well
and not many people actually factored
that into the financial
conditions um but when you do that you
bring about all the good stuff you know
the compounding effect the dollar cost
averaging you smooth out the volatility
of your portfolio so over time
um as long as you start early enough
into the right and well diversified
portfolio you should be able to achieve
your financial goals
eventually because time is a friend and
as long as you can leverage over time
you should be able to participate in
those markets um
and to answer the earlier question i
think it's a classical case of
humans or people working hard for their
money and not allowing their money to
reciprocate because
if you don't put your money to work that
is going to be
did good in your portfolio and that's
not going to help you achieve your
long-term objectives
well thanks so much ava so i mean just a
follow-up question on that since you
mentioned diversification right
and that's also you know a suggestion
that's put forth by
most of the experts interviewed for this
report what do you think is the best
income diversification strategy
to make our money work harder for us
well there isn't a best income approach
every individual is different there's no
cookie cutter solution to anybody there
are however
different levels of risk that one can
consider and participate in i'll just
give you a
rough example a conservative investor
can well
participate in a bond portfolio
a low risk portfolio volatile low
volatility portfolio
and be able to achieve a growth in their
overall asset class
now somebody who is maybe a younger
millennial who is more willing to
participate
in in higher risk products they can
participate in the investment grades
can go into emerging market bonds um
even currencies can play a part in how
you
you you grow your assets so it's
incredibly important for one to
understand your personal risk
how well you sleep at night when you
have that portfolio in place
before you actually execute those uh
income diversification plan but i
totally agree with you diversification
is incredibly important
it can be in real assets it can be in
financial assets it can also be
in options because today there are many
options available
well thank you so much for that you know
i guess it's also very important to both
grow your wealth as well as to protect
your wealth right
um well aber mentioned just now earlier
that time is a passage
of time is our time is a friend you know
for diversification so
dawn as our youngest panelist here and i
know you started financial
planning really early what would you say
to
um to basically your readers out there
about diversification
yeah so i think um when we start early
right
we allow the effects of time to compound
so it makes our job
easier and it's also then um more likely
that we'll sustain the entire journey
because
it's a marathon not a sprint and if we
were to immediately try and accumulate
as much as we can or you know
invest aggressively to achieve huge
returns in a very short period of time
it's very unlikely that that will
sustain so what is more important is
starting early and growing sustainably
through the years
so that our portfolio can then keep
growing to keep up with our lifestyle
explorations as well with our retirement
goals
yeah and you mentioned a really good
point on income diversification as well
so i think for many people right it
would be good for them to start first
with what you think is actually good and
what you enjoy
so we have this thing that we call the
site hustle
right and many of us what we do is you
know we take something that we like or
something that brings us joy
and we do it after our work it could be
um for example if you like baking
and then if you bake well enough and you
bake and soften enough you might start
to find that your friends and family now
wants to buy
your brownies or cookies and that could
be a side hustle that could help
generate income
and for all you know at one point in
time it might even be so successful that
you have
a very strong reason to quit your day
job and go into that full time because
it's earning you a lot more
so it's basically starting from things
that they like and i think with the
internet today there's so many
information out there that one can also
look to do investments whether it is
through their insurance portfolio
whether it's through a financial advisor
or even for people who really want to
diy right some millennials we really we
just want to take on as much as possible
there are all these instruments and
solutions out there that we can use so i
think that's a great way to start
diversification
well thanks so much for that don um well
you you've heard you know so many
good tips from our panelists here let me
just kind of do a quick summary
no shortcut start planning early for
your retirement
think about what you can afford
affordability is key
and time is a friend so you know start
early let that passage of time grow your
wealth
and if you have even more time to spend
um like what don say pick up a side
hustle
you know pick up baking banker by day
baking by night
that can earn you extra income so really
good tips there you know from our
panelists
i'm going to open up the flow to q a
from the audience if you want
if you like to ask a question please
just unmute yourself
and we'll be able to hear your question
from here
any questions from our journalist's
friend
okay while we wait for the first
question i'm just going to carry on my
with my third question which is about
millennia so
don i'm going to stay on you um as you
have seen from the research
three in five millennia surveys say that
they are confident that they have enough
savings for their retirement
and while less than 50 percent of the
older respondents are certain that they
are able to fund the expanded
extended lifespan why do you think this
is the case
i think it's down to two reasons the
first simplistic reason is that um as
news we are more optimistic
and there is exuberance um optimism of
youth so that could be one
but i think the other part would be that
we have a lot more access to information
and solutions to stay so um unlike the
past
where we didn't have the internet and
information was very much restricted
today you can easily go online do a
quick google search and find out all the
different solutions that you can use to
start
um teaching you on how you can begin
your
your retirement portfolio your planning
you know there are all these blogs and
websites and even podcasts nowadays even
youtube channels
um people telling you that you should
say what kind of um techniques or
strategies and hacks
as we call it to get started so there's
a whole range of information out there
and i think with that
in mind that's why we're also starting
to realize the importance of starting
earlier
so when we look at the time horizon we
realize okay it's not that bad because i
don't feel that pressure of having to
save up
a huge amount in a very short period of
time now that i'm starting early say in
their 20s and 30s
okay i have a long runway i even have um
readers coming up to me and they're
literally in jc
or in university and you know they're
talking about starting to invest in
stocks and bonds and i'm like
wow what were we doing when we were back
in university so starting early then
right when they learn from their
mistakes
it will also the mistakes won't be as
crushing
because the earlier you learn them the
better you adapt and therefore using
time
you can then bounce back stronger but
for people who start much later then you
know
all it takes is like one investment
mistake or like
bad luck you know maybe invested in one
stock which went down
and you'll be so traumatized by it that
you're like i only have maybe
20 years or 15 years left and i don't
feel like i can take on that much
risk but when you're young that's a very
different story i'm like okay never mind
i can still try again so i think that
lends to the whole optimism that many
youths generally have
well it's really heartening to know that
you know our younger singaporeans are
actually feeling optimistic about you
know financing for longevity
i mean longevity should be viewed as an
opportunity and not as a challenge right
after all when we have more of life to
enjoy
you know we have more time to spend with
our loved ones we have more time to
spend pursuing our passion
so we really should make use of this
opportunity
you know to make the most out of life so
it's really good to know that you know
our younger singaporeans not only are
they optimistic but
you know to your point they are planning
ahead
um so turning to to to you now able um
staying on the topic of millennials
what's your view
about the findings that three in five
millennias are
optimistic and confident you know about
funding longevity
i i agree with many of the points that
don mentioned early on i think it boils
down to two things
awareness and availability i think don't
touch very well on the fact that there's
a lot
more information because of the
international the the ith that we are in
right now
so there's a lot of market news market
strategies that one can
adapt employ and execute so so that
makes a lot of sense i would also like
to add on to that point the availability
of instruments today um that has that
has grown tremendously
um since probably my time uh
and and and and i remember the days when
i first started work
the the amount of funds available in the
markets was was
you can count in your hands today there
are so many players in the market with
different styles and strategies they
invest in different markets
so i think that the availability of
instruments uh today
has has brought us to a whole new level
awareness
um i think the the the government and
the private sector has done a really
good job
in bringing awareness to the millennials
to to highlight to them
the risk of not planning ahead um and
not expecting the unforeseen
and not being able to sustain your lives
or your desired lifestyle
in your golden years so i think the
awareness bit the education that the
government and the private sector has
done
has done a really good job in bringing
the awareness back up yep i agree with
that i think
you know financial education is so
important you know to make sure that
people are actually safe for the long
term
in fact i think um the awareness of
financial planning is so high here
that in the report you know what we're
seeing is that 80 80
of the respondent and that includes
millennia they are listing health care
as their top
saving priority so they're not saving
for trevor
or you know uh um for a a lavish
lifestyle they are actually saving for
health care
um dennis what are your views on this
you know healthcare being a top saving
priority for respondents
i think based on the feedback from from
this survey and so many people are
looking at saving towards
healthcare right so four out of five are
doing that it's
personally not a surprise to me and i
think it's important because
we are looking at living longer and
potentially we might be living some
time in our long in our golden years
in ill health so it's important that we
start saving towards that
from an early stage i think the facts
remain that
the whole population is aging so
as we go through that that that
phenomenal that that is a worldwide
phenomenon so that's something that we
have to be
prepared for and in order to factor that
in we just need to understand that
not only are people living longer but
the the years
in chronic ill health potentially right
so compared to say 10 years 20 years 30
years ago i think people
with longevity they are spending a bit
more years
in in the golden age in ill health so
that's something that we have to be
prepared for
secondly i think it's importantly the
whole notion of um
inflation and in particular medical
inflation
so that again is a reality right so as
as the
society becomes more affluent and as we
consume healthcare
and over time over the passage of time
the inflation will continue to rise
so we've got to look at the longevity
and having that ill health
in our old age against the backdrop of
of this whole scenario in terms of
rising uh inflation
and finally i think it's important for
all of us to take charge of our own
health
and our own lives so it's important to
kind of work towards um
prevention protection and postponement
so i say again right prevention
protection
and postponement of diseases or ill
health
and the way to tackle that is taking
personal responsibility
and working with a partner right so
working with your insurance provider
your healthcare provider taking charge
yourself to really work towards your
overall
well-being your overall health
and by doing that you're able to
postpone some of these things
and therefore your expenditure for your
medical
services will be low will be kept low
thanks dennis thank you
yep i guess it's true that you know um
what we always say health is wealth
right
there is no point in being financially
prepared
if you don't have the health to enjoy it
so definitely you know to take good care
of our health so you start young to stay
younger
um i see now we have a question from the
inheritable caroline
caroline would you like to unmute
yourself and ask your question
hi can you hear me yes we can hear you
loud and clear
okay great um my question is to go three
panelists
because um you guys just mentioned that
many of the
research findings are not
hi caroline we lost you for a few
seconds do you mind repeating your
question
um
yes we can hear you now okay
um i'm just just like you asked
my three panelists what is the most um
what's the most surprising result
findings
would anybody like to start first i can
go first um
so for me when i actually look at the
results of the study i thought it was
very
interesting that um millennials
generally want to have more career
breaks
like i do see that happening among my
peers and the people that i know
but never realized that this was
actually a broader trend and
it makes sense you know like um i think
you tie in with a lot of different
factors traveling
for sure it's one with the affordability
of travel and our desire to live
more fulfilling lives experiencing the
world um there's also another trend of
you know mothers taking a break from
work
because when they have kids um they may
want to take a step back and spend more
time with them and if we contract this
to the past where my
parents have many children compared to
parents having just one or two
today they tend to be more anxious
social media doesn't really help all of
that so you know
we want to take that break and having
the financial ability to do so is a huge
uh decision uh factor that actually
leads us to decide whether or not we
should do that
so i think that part on the career
breaks is definitely true with
technology with all the different trends
in place i think we're going to start
seeing a lot of that
happening more often now well thanks
dawn
and taking a career break to take a side
hustle right
that's probably one of the coming up
trend as well
yeah i think there was a lawyer in in
japan that actually
uh um started a chocolate or a bakery
henry compete now she's one of the most
successful
bakery in the whole of tokyo and she was
formerly a top-notch lawyer and then she
decided to
say you know that's it i'm i'm going to
pursue my passion i'm going to start
making uh cakes macons and stuff like
that
and she's not super popular i believe
they have a branch or so in singapore as
well
you know andre carpentier something like
that
yeah interesting so how about you know
dennis abel um in a response to a
caroline question
any particular insights findings that
you find
that is surprising well from my
perspective
i think what is most surprising to me
is actually the speed of this happening
and the attitude of the young the
millennials and the younger singaporeans
having this concept of a multi-stage
life
i mean it is something that we've been
talking about and know that that's
coming but
what this confirms to me is surprising
why because it's really accelerating
what it means is that traditionally
we've been always thinking about that
three-stage life right study study study
you work work work
and then you retire retire you retire
but now it's kind of like a multi-stage
life
you kind of study but you're trying to
bring work into study
by trying to bring work environment
while you're in classroom and likewise
when we are working
we're bringing classroom into work right
and people
also right like what don shared about
earlier people kind of taking career
breaks
right from their from their work and
then trying to upgrade themselves
upskill study and all that
so so this three-part thing
traditionally is now kind of
in in this whole melting pot and it
becomes like a multi-stage
situation so i think that is very
interesting insight
and it's important therefore then for us
to be
focusing on our financial planning and
that discipline towards that financial
planning process
in order to support this multi-stage
life
thanks dennis that's really really true
what about
what are you able well for me i think
most of the findings are pretty much in
line with some of the expectations we
already have
at least on an advisory standpoint um
but
perhaps the one that i would pick up is
three out of five millennials that
actually
uh feel that they are ready for for
retirement
um as a possible older respondent
i now know that a bowl of
a plate of chicken rice back then
formally a dollar
can now cost five times more so
having said that this same five dollars
plate of chicken rice
could well be costing fifteen twenty
dollars
in in twenty thirty years time um so
have they
actually factored that in because
inflation is very often
and then biologists this is a human
phenomenon we tend to underestimate a
lot of things
we tend to underestimate the impact of
inflation we tend to underestimate the
power of compounding
and as a result of which when you reach
the stage when you say all right
when i'm going to retire you realize
that wait hang on i may not have enough
to last me a hundred so what do i do
then
so so so i um perhaps the exuberance
that you you
earlier pointed out that maybe the
millennials feel that oh you know i'm
young i've got a lot of runway
i can do anything i'm invincible but i
guess
maybe a little bit of caution might be
warranted that you know you might not be
able to achieve your end goal
if you don't start thinking a lot deeply
about inflation
about compounding and even black swan
events which will happen
along the way yeah okay so a lot for
millennials to think about
so dennis um just again i mean this
topic of millennia is like you know i
think something that's really
interesting
um you know abel mentioned again three
and five millennia say that they are
confident to to save to 100.
um and not only are they confident but
they seem to want everything right i
mean
they they have a responsibility towards
their family which is good they want to
take care of their parents they want to
take care of their children
and they don't even expect their
children to take care of them you know
so that's sort of like
financial independence that they seek
and yet they want to take career break
they want to travel
they want to do a side hustle they want
to pursue their passion
do you think it's realistic you know to
do all of this
for the millennia well firstly i think i
really commend the millennials for
having that kind of
notion they want to save they want to
take care of themselves
they want to take care of their family
but at the same time they want to have a
bit of fun they want to
take career breaks they want to pursue
their life passion
i think that that is fantastic and my
short answer is that
i personally think that is doable that
is very doable
but with a caveat right the caveat is
that they have to plan
they have to plan early and they need to
have that disciplined approach
towards that planning i think if they
are committed to that
the multi-stage life that we talked
about earlier i think that that would
definitely be a very real
reality right in in as they have that
passage to us uh
living to a hundred um i think it's also
important that
to achieve that the millennials may want
to also start thinking about
being comfortable to invest right
because
um right some people don't quite um
want to invest or they are not
comfortable in doing so right so but we
all know that the notion of
spreading your risk right don't put all
your eggs in one basket
so taking a very risky form
right of your portfolio is one extreme
but i would argue and say that
having no investments in the portfolio
everything is just
for example just cash right and then
with the ongoing inflation and all that
we just earlier discussed
that will then probably be a risk
towards the
young people having this thought of i
want to save to 100 i want to do my
career break and do all these wonderful
stuff
but i do not quite want to take risks so
i think that there must be some
action taken for them to start pivoting
towards that and today in this day and
age
i think abel has talked about that
earlier there are a lot more options out
there in the marketplace compared to
many years ago
and also bite size opportunities
bite-size investment savings insurance
opportunities
to get you started first so i think the
important thing is to get started
earlier younger and to focus on their
longer runway
thanks dennis um again very very good
tips there and what i pick up on you
know
take risks and take actions sometimes we
know what to do but then you just
you know you have so much inertia and
you don't actually start to take action
so you know and if you start to plan
late you are really too late you know
for for planning for your retirement
i think we have a question from
jacqueline nuttgruff
um
okay well she's type of question how has
covet and the
economic downturn impacted saving for
retirement how does this differ
among the different age groups and what
should they do
well when we start when we started this
research it was actually just at the
onset of
covet you know so we didn't actually
have an opportunity to ask
respondents how they feel about covert
but we can ask the panelists here
you know what they think you know of of
how has covet and economic downturn
impacted saving for retirement
maybe i have a step at this first um i i
think kovit has really showed up quite a
lot of weaknesses and and failures
um in the entire ecosystem
but more importantly kovit has further
emphasized the need of having that rainy
day cash
in fact today it's not a rainy day
anymore it's it's a real downpour that
we're facing right now
and you and six months of savings
may not be enough and and this is
reality
um even our government's coming out to
tell us that there
will be further um companies closing
down there'll be further unemployment
and that's going to exacerbate the
current situation that we are facing
today
um what is important however that if you
for a different age group
if you had not started investing or
saving
early early in the game you do not have
that buffer
and you may be facing financial
difficulties going forward now if you
are the luckier few or maybe the more
aware of you who has started investing a
lot of savings a lot earlier
your portfolio should a well-diversified
portfolio
should be able to weather this volatile
times
now if you look at the current market
situation
we are really experiencing a k recovery
no we talk about a u a v
a w really it's a k recovery the um
industries are actually not doing well
and will not continue to do well
and maybe permanently out of the game
for for the long period of time
but on the contrary companies that are
very well plugged in
into the it space um the e-commerce
space
those companies are doing really really
well and that's you and enhance you see
that the upward uh think in terms of
recovery so so
for investors if you're not diversified
again you may be participating in the
wrong trend and at the end of the day
um having the black zone event of the
unlucky event that you mentioned
and be losing a lot of your retirement
funds conversely if you had a
well-diversified portfolio
if you're invested into the downtrend
that's fine because
not all of all your assets are exposed
to this single downtrend
but the uptrends may actually buffer or
smooth out that downside volatility so
it's incredibly important that
one starts early and diversify your
assets across different
classes oh thanks abel um dennis any any
views on what abel has just you know
mentioned about diversification
absolutely i think i think that that is
really important in terms of
diversification and
the reality that kovit has brought about
to to the world and to all of us is
um you know even as we speak there are
people who have
been displaced out of their roles that
their jobs
savings have been declining but i think
the
the one impact about covid and how it
has shaped us
is our attitude towards savings and our
attitude towards our own portfolio
and i think the importance of having
that plan
right because um it's only through these
challenging situations and if you were
well prepared for it
right you'll probably be able to weather
through a little bit longer so i think
covet has has shaken everyone up and
drove home the importance of being
prepared being prepared earlier so
that's one
second one i think it's it's also this
notion of having
sort of vivid sources of income and then
kind of
active and passive income right the the
risk is too great if you have just
one main source of income it's good to
have
some other passive sources so like what
don uh shared earlier as well in terms
of baking and stuff like that so
i think whatever ways right big ways
small ways that doesn't matter
but kind of how else do you relook and
diversify your sources of income
i think that is important and critically
the other one is also
even though you may have a financial
plan already review that plan
review that plan so what i've heard in
the recent period in the covid
situation and especially back in second
quarter when we had
the circuit breaker the lockdown whereby
people were kind of confined to their
homes
i heard of many friends and and
associates who actually
took the time to since they're at home
right it's a lot easier for them to
go and retrieve and get organized right
bank statements
insurance policies all the different
documentations
and kind of go through that on their own
and talk to your trusted advisor
right so going through that whole
process and i think a lot of them have
kind of
realized that actually they are under
underprotected
right or they are not just adequately
prepared in various parts of their
portfolio or their lives
i think that is a very very important
thing that kovit has kind of struck home
and finally i think one one other point
to share is um
investing in ourselves skills right so
beyond i mean
we talked a lot in the earlier few
questions and order about
health about wealth and all that but i
think importantly
given cov what has taught us is also
invest in ourselves
and in our own skill sets skill set we
have to continuously
upgrade upskill reskill and as long as
we stay relevant
relevant in the industry relevant in the
company we will be able to continue to
be financially
self-sufficient in that sense so
learning is going to be a lifelong
process
it's no longer like the three part that
i talked about earlier whereby
in the past it's just first part of life
learn learn learn in school
but it's going to be a continuous
upgrading process and in so doing
we keep ourselves relevant and we are
financially independent
thanks so much dennis dawn do you have
anything to add to that
yeah i mean i think eva and dennis took
a lot of the words out of my mouth
of what i would have said as well um but
i think i just want to add a little bit
more color on what they mentioned which
is that
i think kovit has shown us the need for
diversification not just across
incomes but also in terms of investments
right sometimes the problem is that when
we
plan um we get stuck on our plan and we
expect everything to go our way
so say for example the four percent we
travel rule people have started to
realize
hey that's not so good anymore because
you know when banks or all the different
companies start
having financial issues and they cut the
dividend you're not going to be able to
rely on your four percent withdrawal to
finance your retirement anymore
so it's about being agile right and
adapting well and the other thing is
that you know when we diversify across
investments as well everyone knows that
you have to
buy low sell high but let's let's face
it how many people were actually
prepared to buy low when the market low
truly presented itself
so aside from just recognizing the
opportunity um it's
having the resources to be able to take
charge
of that opportunity to be able to move
forward those who had
uh save up those who had made sure that
they had that safety net and that buffer
they were able to go in during the
downturn of the market crash and it
doesn't matter whether they went in
anytime between
february march or april even may their
portfolio would be significantly up at
this point in time if they had
diversified across
industries so that's something that you
know i see a lot of people these days
we know and there's a huge growth in
awareness but how many of us are
actually taking
real action we're just sitting on the
sideline and say i'll do it tomorrow i'm
young i still have time
but the truth is um you need that start
getting prepared now otherwise when the
opportunity presents itself
you won't be able to take charge of it
and then if anything else
happens at the same time as well imagine
if you lose your job
or if you were to be hit by a health
crisis at this point in time
you're going to find that you're very
very stressed so i think you know this
whole survey and this
um kovit has really shown us the light
on all these different strategies and
made
us rethink and re-question ourselves
what do we need to change
what more do we need to do and how we
cannot be stuck
on just one fixed strategy itself
throughout the rest of our life
yeah thanks dawn i think if anything
covet has taught us is to be agile and
adaptable
and definitely you know open to change
okay we have a couple of questions one
from asia advisors network and one from
the business times
i'm going to take the question from the
asia advisors network first
from mita her question is how will
insurance help in being financially
prepared for
increasing longevity i think that
question
would have to be responded by dennis
absolutely
happy to do that how will insurance
products help
us be financially more prepared right so
i think two three things to kind of uh
talk through one is actually when we
look at the insurance
coverage that we have been getting
traditionally
right as you review your own portfolio
as you review your own plans that were
purchased
i think it's important that with this
backdrop of living to a hundred
will the policies that you have actually
support that
because not many policies potentially
out there could be doing that
and that's one reason why at prudential
we have been
focusing on this in the recent years and
many of our products now actually
cover our policy holders up to a hundred
right up to a hundred and gives the
option to the policy holder
and you're able to customize these
solutions to work towards this
this this fact that we are living longer
right so that's one from a product
construct perspective
and secondly of course in terms of the
different kinds of policies that
insurance companies will have
some of it will be more savings
endowment related
and that will be a one avenue one strong
avenue
for the policyholders or the public to
consider using that to work towards
their financial plans
and finally one other thought is i think
it's is
we talked a lot about health and wealth
earlier but when you talk about wealth a
lot of people focus
on their efforts in generating the
wealth
but i think equally what is important is
as you generate the wealth
you have to protect the wealth you have
to protect the wealth and that's where
insurance products potentially comes
into play as well
so don't get me wrong it's important to
generate the wealth but generating debt
and having no protection over it
it's also a risk that uncertain times
and all that that potentially may be
wiped out
so it's important to have these two
notions in mind as we generate the
wealth
how do you also protect that wealth so
that's where insurance products
potentially come into play
thanks dennis thank you mita i hope that
answers your question
next i'm going to go to a question from
genevieve the business times
what can companies do to support this
leaving to 100 expectation or trend
would anybody like to respond to that
question
i can go first so um i think as a
millennial
we're starting to see a lot of trends
that are probably going to be
increasingly common
in the coming years and uh it would be
great when our as
our employers our company um as much as
they can try to support that so
traditionally companies have always
offered um
insurance products for their employees
itself is part of the
benefits but i think we're starting to
see um upskilling as a very valuable
tool as well
so companies who invest on helping their
employees ease up skill be it a
subscription to coursera or any other
learning courses
out there this is going to become
increasingly valuable and will also help
towards employment branding
and attract these people to go and work
for them because we're realizing that we
cannot remain stagnant
i think the other thing is also
flexibility um
one thing i have to say is that i'm
thankful kovit has shown
that it's possible for your employees to
work from home
because a lot of us especially when we
become parents we really struggle with
trying to care for young children
and doing our best at work and for
companies who are very stuck in the
traditional mindset of not allowing that
flexibility
it then comes to a point whereby we just
have to say well i have to choose
between my work
or my child and usually family would
come first
so with this whole change um companies
who do offer that kind of flexibility i
think are going to be
highly in demand and they will really go
a long way in helping millennials to you
know be loyal
um and helping them to adapt and balance
all the different things that they have
on their plate
yeah so with side hustles as well you
know in the past we always say
moonlighting was a crime
right don't get caught but i think today
with more people doing it and
showing that necessity for having more
than one income stream
companies will actually support that and
of course as long as it doesn't affect
the employee's job i think that is the
reasonable expectation to have here
but companies who are more flexible on
that i think they're gonna see that they
will get
more millennials employees supportive of
them and wanting to stay on because we
do appreciate all of this
yeah well thanks so much don thank you
dennis would you like to share something
about what prudential is doing you know
to support
uh leaving to 100 i think one of the
things
companies can do to support this living
to a hundred
is again back to the notion of what was
discussed earlier the
so-called traditional three-stage life
into this increasingly multi-stage life
so what that means is with the
multi-stage life it doesn't mean that
someone
traditionally in this last stage whereby
we say retirement retirement return
means
they may want to just purely retire
because in those
golden years they some of them maybe
they're 60 over here so or 70 years
or what not they may still potentially
want to work so one of the things
actually companies can do is to kind of
review the retirement age
or the retirement policy so that one
thing potential singapore has done is
actually to remove
our retirement age so technically
there's
no retirement age in the company and for
all our fellow colleagues whoever who
want to work
it's a merit-based process memory-based
system and everybody can continue to
work right so there isn't any
retirement age of sorts in that sense
and for us
as an insurer to better support this
notion
it's actually to support companies out
there
to do this and one of the things is
actually in the recent period recent
years what we have done is
for our group policies whereby we are
insuring
our companies out there whereby
companies are purchasing the group
insurance from us as an insurer we also
remove that
age for these employees of the companies
so they can actually cover their
employees up to 800
right unlike traditional policy whereby
you kept it at a certain age and all
that
so there's one small contribution that
we are doing to help support this notion
of
what companies can do to support the
living to 100.
oh thanks dennis well indeed right i
mean if you're all leaving to 100
retiring at 62 that leaves us another 40
years
of life to leave and you know to retire
for 40 years that's a really really long
time
i wouldn't know what to do with all that
time if i'm not working
well hey but do you have anything to add
to that i would i would probably just
chime in that companies could actually
start focusing a lot on education
in the sense that you bring up the
awareness of the the financial needs
that
you're going to have be engagement of
external parties
engagement of internal hr resources to
educate the people the
of the importance of having a proper
financial plan
um how you build a passive income
portfolio because once you retire and
and
at most points you will retire at some
point
when you can't exchange human capital
for a salary you need the passive income
to kick in
but if nobody teaches you or educates
you or brings up the awareness that you
need to
create that passive income portfolio
when you reach retirement you realize
that hang on i do not have
that passive income stream should i
start building it now
a bit too late so as long as you're a
contributing employee for a company
today and
uh it's actually a company's
responsibility to be able to educate you
through to to different uh matters to
your hr to the management structure
but if companies can do that people will
be a lot more prepared
and capable of living to 100.
well thank you so much um genevieve i
hope that answered your question and
just a very quick recap
what the panelists said earlier on about
what companies can do to support leaving
to
employees leaving to 100. one
invest in upscaling the workforce make
sure that the employees
are ready future ready for the economy
that they can actually stay productive
for longer
um two scrapping the retirement age you
know
make it the choice of the employees to
work for as long as they want as long as
they perform
so don't have a mandatory retirement age
at 62 or 65
and finally to raise awareness on
financial education
among the workforce make sure that
employees are educated about not just
about
working but also you know how to save
and how to invest
their hard-earned salary and hard-earned
money
so thank you very much for all of that
advice
do we have another any other questions
from the journalists
um i see here no further question uh i'm
going to then wrap up the panna
discussion with one last
question one last question perhaps for
dennis well when we first started this
research
three years ago in in 2018 you know one
of the questions that we asked
respondents were do you want to leave up
to 100
and interestingly only one third of them
say that they want to leave up to 100
actually a lot of them are very afraid
you know they're like oh 100 no no i
don't want to leave that long
because you know i may not be healthy
enough i may not be wealthy enough so
just want to get you know
um your perspective what would you say
to people who are
afraid you know to leave up to 100
what advice would you give them well
from my perspective i would say
this is a reality right so
with medical science improving
digital and all of that the the fact
remains that
we will continue to live and we will
start living longer and longer
so from my perspective it will be
embrace
embrace this whole notion of living to a
hundred embrace it as
an opportunity right rather more like a
challenge look at the opportunities
embrace that
and work towards that with your own
personal financial planning
and we will look at embracing this i'm
also looking at it
holistically right so this whole notion
of living to a hundred
embracing it holistically means not just
looking at the
health part of it not also just the
wealth part of it
but also upgrading yourself your skills
part of it
and also the social part of it so what
do i mean by that right the health is
quite a straightforward thing right so
living to 100
with medical science now being better
with technology
so how can we use technology to to
better
live longer but well live well right so
so that is for health for wealth i think
the panelists have
discussed that earlier as well so there
are many different techniques and all
that but in short
get started get started early get
started with a plan
and work towards a plan and review that
plan accordingly
over time and having that discipline i
think
the other one that we talked about is
the other than health and wealth is the
skills
right so so as we live towards a hundred
it's important to also invest in
ourselves
invest in our skill set because a
hundred can be a quite a long time
right so so things will change over time
so how do we continue to
evolve and stay relevant and in order to
stay relevant we have to
upskill and reskill ourselves and by so
doing
we are constantly relevant relevant in
society relevant in the companies
relevant in the workforce that will
enable us to be very
financially independent and finally i
talked a little bit about the social
part earlier
right the social meaning the first three
are quite tangible so social part is
kind of
what i'm saying is invest in the intel
the intangible invest in in the family
invest in your relationships invest
socially
build that social network around you and
also then
the community and giving back right so
that that makes living to 100
very purposeful and and yeah so i think
these will be the few
pointers i will share with that audience
in terms of
embracing the opportunities of living
saving and preparing 400. well thanks
very much dennis
um i mean we've touched on a lot of the
key points we touch on wealth
uh health we touch on skills wouldn't
actually talk so much about relationship
you know during the panda discussion but
i think that's a really good point
and also a very important point as well
because
we all know that you know social
isolation in oh
is a big problem and and if you're going
to have a very long life you do want to
have your friends and your families and
you know that whole social support
around you
and sometimes we forget you know about
investing in relationship because we're
so busy doing
so many different things so thank you
for bringing up that point you know i
think that's a really really important
point
you know for all of us to take away with
and with that
we've come to the end of the media
launch of saving for 100
funding longevity in a time of
uncertainty so thank you very much for
joining us today
we hope you found the research insights
meaningful and also interesting and that
you will inspire you to have
conversations and dialogues with your
friends and family
about saving for 100. thank you
[Music]
you